Ram Kumar Dubey Cloud Data Architect/ Data Engineer

Contact no: +91- 7835994381 Email: ramsoft73@gmail.com

Highly skilled and results-oriented Specialized in cloud technologies, automation, and ensuring high availability and performance of critical databases.

13 years of experience as Data Architect & Cloud of successful career in Administrating & Development(Python, SQL), Data Analyst, Data Eng.

Certification:

- AWS certified Solution Architect Associate.
- AZURE Administrator Associate
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Database Administrator Associate.
- Microsoft Certified Database Administrator for SQL Server 2008.
- Microsoft Certified Solution Associate SQL Server 2012.
- Oracle Certified Professional (OCP)

Professional Skill Experience:

- Total 13 year's experience in Database Development, Database Administration and Data Engineering.
- Since 5 years working as Data Cloud Architect using different platforms: AWS, Azure.
- 3 year's experience in DevOps using Git, Terraform, CI/CD Pipelines: Jenkins, GitHub, Azure DevOps.
- Data Modeling tools such as Erwin, Microsoft Visio, and SQL Server Management Studio to create and maintain data models and diagrams for complex systems.
- Monitoring & Alerting: CloudWatch, Azure Monitor.
- High Availability & Disaster Recovery: Failover Clustering, Always On, Replication
- Database Security: Encryption, Access Control, Audit Logging
- Performance Tuning: Query Optimization, Indexing, Resource Allocation
- Expertise in RDBMS (SQL Server, Oracle, MySQL.) and NoSQL database (like MongoDB, DynamoDB).
- Development skills in SQL, PL/SQL, ETL and Azure Data factory, Azure synapse.
- implementation experience in building multi-tenant Azure cloud services using components such as app services, IoT Hub, Stream Analytics, Azure Functions, Service Bus Queue, Cosmos DB, Azure SQL, Blob Storage, Key Vault, Redis-Cache, IOT Edge, API-Management Service and Azure AD.
- Design scalable, reliable data pipelines using Azure Data Factory, Synapse, and Data Lake.
- Architect ML models with cloud integration for business use cases using Azure ML.
- Design Data lakes/warehouses for batch and real-time processing.
- Integrate AI models with real-time data systems (Azure Event Hub, Stream Analytics).
- Build AI solutions using Azure AI services (Cognitive Services, OpenAI Service).
- Integrate AI models with real-time data systems (Azure Event Hub, Stream Analytics).
- Ensure high availability, fault tolerance, and disaster recovery using Azure services.
- Cloud Ecosystem: AWS (EC2, EMR, Lambda, Athena, Glue, Redshift and 53).
- Deploy real-time data pipelines with Azure Event Hub, Stream Analytics, and Kafka.
- Design data integration strategies using Azure Data Factory and APIs.
- Optimize distributed data processing with Apache Spark on Azure Databricks.
- Improve query performance in Synapse with partitioning, indexing, and caching.

- Implement CI/CD pipelines in Azure DevOps.
- Developed ETL processes to integrate structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data into a unified data warehouse, performing data profiling, quality assessments, and collaborating on database tuning and query optimization to enhance reporting accuracy and system performance.
- I have done training on Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Data Structures, Algorithms.

Technical Skill:

Database	MS SQL Server 2005-2022, Oracle, MYSQL, MongoDB, Cassandra, DynamoDB, PostgreSQL	
ETL	SSIS, ETL, ADF	
Reporting Tools	SSRS, Power BI, Azure Synapse	
Programming	Python , Apache Spark , Scala	
Language		
Tools & Utilities	SSMS, SSDT, VS, Git, TFS, Visio, SQLSENTRY	
Cloud	Azure, AWS	
Scripting Language	Unix shell script, Terraform,Ansible	
Big data	HDFS, Apache spark, Scala	
Operating system	Window, Linux, Unix	

Professional Experience:

Employer	Duration	Designation
Datamatics Global Services Ltd	03/2022 – Present	Lead Consultant - Cloud Data Architect
Nice Interactive Solution Pvt. Ltd, Pune	01/2019 - 01/2022	Specialist Cloud Database engineer
TSYS, Pune	02/2016 – 12/2018	Distributed Database Administrator
,		Senior
Smart Utility Services Pvt.Ltd, Noida	05/2014 – 11/2015	SQL DBA & Developer
Sunsha Technologies Pvt.Ltd Gurgaon	04/2011 – 04/2014	SQL DBA & Developer

Projects Details:

1) Client - SAIA

Duration April 2023 - till date

Role – Cloud Data Architect

Developed and implemented a scalable, end-to-end data pipeline on **Microsoft Azure** that handled both real-time and batch data processing for integrating data from multiple sources (REST APIs, IoT sensors, databases).

The pipeline was designed for an event-driven architecture to ensure real-time responses to critical events while handling large-scale batch processing for data aggregation and analytics.

Delivered a high-performance, scalable, and event-driven data architecture on Azure Cloud, enabling real-time analytics, batch processing for large datasets, and integration from diverse data sources. The system processed millions of real-time events daily with low latency and supported batch ETL for historical analysis, contributing to the real-time decision-making and long-term data strategy.

Technologies Used: Python, Machine Learning, Azure Event Hubs, Azure Stream Analytics, Azure Data Factory, Databricks, Azure Functions, Azure Service Bus, Azure Data Lake Storage (ADLS), Azure SQL Database, Synapse Analytics, Azure Monitor, Power BI, Azure Logic Apps

2) Client - Summit Digital Systems Ltd May 2023 - Oct 2023 Role - Cloud Data Architect

- I have worked on-premises Databases servers to administrating and monitoring/troubleshooting the servers to use SQL sentry and Redgate tool.
- Azure data migration task to collaborated with stakeholders to gather requirements for the Inventory module data migration.
- Conducted a thorough analysis of existing data structures, dependencies, and business rules. Leveraged Azure Data Factory for orchestrating and automating the data migration workflows.
- Utilized Azure Data Lake Storage for efficient and scalable data storage.
- Implemented data transformations and processing using Azure Data Bricks with a combination of Python and Scala.

Technologies Used:

Azure Services: Azure Data Factory, Azure Synapse, Azure Data Lake Storage (ADLS), Azure DataBricks, Azure Logic Apps, Azure SQL Database, Azure Key Vault.

• Programming Languages: Python, Scala, SQL • Integration: Logic App, REST APIs

3) Client - UNICEF (Duration – (April 2022 – April 2023)

Role - Cloud Data Architect and Migration Lead

- Implement and migrate database solutions as per best practices.
- Interacted with end customers and gathering requirements for Designing and developing common architecture for storing Retail data within Enterprise and building Data Lake in Azure cloud
- Developed Geo Tracker applications using PySpark to integrate data coming from other sources like ftp, csv files processed using Azure Databricks and written into Snowflake.
- Developed Spark applications for data extraction, transformation and aggregation from multiple systems and stored on Azure Data Lake Storage using Azure Databricks notebooks
- Worked on Spark with Scala and converted into Pyspark Code for Geo tracker
- Written Unzip and decode functions using Spark with Scala and parsing the xml files into Azure blog storage
- Developed PySpark scripts from source system like Azure Event Hub to ingest data in reload, append, and merge mode into Delta tables in Databricks
- Optimized PySpark applications on Databricks, which yielded a significant amount of cost reduction
 Created Pipelines in ADF to copy parquet files from ADLS Gen2 location to Azure Synapse Analytics Data Warehouse.

4) Nice integrative Products and services Role – Specialist Cloud Data Engineer

Duration – (Jan 2019 – Dec 2021)

- Experience in implement database migration from on-premises to cloud (AWS) Environment.
- Experience on Always ON, Clustering, Replication and troubleshooting production issues.
- Experience required on Patching & Upgrade on standalone, mirrored and cluster environment.

- Experience in SQL Server migration from lower to higher SQL Server versions.
- Experience in troubleshooting and resolving database integrity issues, performance issues, blocking and deadlocking issues, replication issues, log shipping issues, connectivity issues, and security issues
- Ability to detect and troubleshoot SQL Server CPU, memory, I/O, disk space, and other resource contentions and allow restrict resource thru resource management.
- Directed integration of diverse data sources into a unified data warehouse, successfully providing a single source of truth used by various departments for critical decision-making on snowflake data warehouse.
- Architected a Follow and Notify (FAN) application in AWS using VPC, S3, Route 53, Auto-scaling, Elastic Beanstalk, SQS, SNS, RDS, and DMS,SMS, Redshift,AWS Glue,EMR
- Involved in building security model, VPC, Elastic IP for databases on Cloud platform.

5) ProPayProducts and Services:

Role - Data Architect & Administrator

My Contribution:

- Worked in Agile methodologies and support to Development team to Add new functionality in Product.
- Collaborated with development teams to design and implement data models, develop complex SQL queries, and manage SQL database administration tasks to ensure data integrity and optimize performance.
- Implement CI/CD pipeline in TFS and Maintiain Branch till Prod.
- Used Database Engine Tuning Advisor (DTA), Dynamic Management Views (DMVs), SQL Profiler.
- Worked on automating Critical Applications Health Check report using T-SQL and Power shell script.
- Created SQL Job, Schedules and Alerts using SQL Server Agent and DB Email.
- Implementation of Database Maintenance Plans for database integrity checks, update statistics and re-indexing and Clean-up Activities.
- Implementation of Database Partition, Scheduled Jobs to add New Partition, Data Files and File groups.
- Performed Daily Activities Database Backup/Restore, Scheduling and Monitoring Jobs and SSIS packages.

Educational Qualification:

 B.TECH from Shambhunath Institute of Engineering & Technology, Allahabad (U.P.Technical University) in 2008 with 67.75%

Personal Profile:

Father's Name: Mr. Dinesh Kumar Dubey

Gender, DOB: Male, 12th July 1987 Languages Known: Hindi, English

Hobbies: Sports, watching movies, Learn technical stuff

Current City: Noida

Date: Ram Kumar Dubey